<?xml version="1.0"?>
<collections>
  <collection>
    <h3 id="chicagojazzarchive">Chicago Jazz Archive</h3>

    <p><span class="snippet">The Chicago Jazz Archive was founded in 1976 to
preserve materials on the birth and early growth of Chicago jazz.</span> Over
time, due in part to a relationship with the Jazz Institute of Chicago, the
collections have grown to span more than eight decades of Chicago and general
jazz history. The collections include recordings, publications, photographs,
articles, posters, programs, ticket stubs, and other ephemera of musicians,
clubs, record companies, and jazz organizations. In 2007-2008, the collections
of the Chicago Jazz Archive were transferred to the Special Collections
Research Center.  Chicago Jazz Archive manuscript and archival collections are
currently being processed as part of the Uncovering New Chicago Archives
Project (UNCAP), a three-year initiative funded by the Andrew W.  Mellon
Foundation. These changes will enable the Library to provide expanded access to
the Chicago Jazz Archive, utilizing the facilities, services, and staff of the
Special Collections Research Center.</p>
  </collection>
  <collection>
    <h3 id="contemporarypoetry">Contemporary Poetry</h3>

    <p><span class="snippet">The Special Collections Research Center of the
University of Chicago Library is continuing to expand the scope of its archives
of modern poetry.</span> Building on the editorial files of Poetry: A Magazine
of Verse, Special Collections is responding to new academic programs in
creative writing and modern poetry by focusing on the work of poetry editors
and the archives of modern poetry journals.  These holdings now include the
editorial files of Chicago Review, which include letters and writings of Diane
Ackerman, Robert Bly, William Burroughs, Paul Carroll, Gregory Corso, Robert
Creeley, Diane DiPrima, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Allen Ginsberg, Thom Gunn, Jack
Kerouac, Maxine Kumin, Denise Levertov, Philip Levine, Howard Nemerov, Kenneth
Patchen, Robert Pinsky, Kenneth Rexroth, and James Tate.  The professional
papers of poet and editor Paul Carroll include a significant group of materials
related to Carroll's editorship of Big Table.  The papers of writer, poet,
essayist and photographer Layle Silbert document her well-known photographs of
poets and writers.</p>
  </collection>
  <collection>
    <h3 id="mappingthestacks">Mapping The Stacks</h3>

    <p><span class="snippet">Beginning at the University of Chicago in Fall
2003, Mapping the Stacks (MTS) was led by Professor Jacqueline Goldsby when she
was Associate Professor in English Language &amp; Literature and the College of
the University of Chicago.</span> Recognizing that the city of Chicago is
teeming with archives devoted to mid-20th century African American life but
that these institutions and organizations often lack the staff and funding
required to keep their collections fully accessible to the public, MTS aims to
bridge this gap.</p>

    <p>Bringing together faculty and Ph.D. students with field expertise in
African American Studies and a deep interest in archival collection
development, MTS provides labor power to:</p>

    <ul class="bullets">
      <li>Survey and identify African-American primary source materials (books,
films, photographs, newspapers, magazines, manuscript archives, recorded oral
histories, and other ephemera) housed in Chicago-area institutions and
community-based organizations that are in need of processing and
cataloguing</li>
      <li>Process collections using field-approved archival management
methods</li>
      <li>Produce and disseminate finding aids to facilitate public access to these collections via print and web sources</li>
    </ul>

    <p><a href="http://mts.lib.uchicago.edu/">Visit the Mapping the Stacks website</a>.</p>
  </collection>
</collections>
