<?xml version="1.0"?>
<institutions>
  <institution>
    <h3 id="chicagodefender">About the Chicago Defender</h3>
    <p><span class="snippet">Founded by Robert S. Abbott in 1905, the Chicago
Defender is one of America's longest-running African American
newspapers.</span> The Defender is best known for having spurred the Great
Migration of African Americans from the southern United States to the nation's
urban centers in the north--especially Chicago--during the first decades of the
20th century. The Defender also paved the way for the modernization of the
Black press, given its capital resources; advanced printing technologies;
national and international distribution networks; and multi-cultural,
transnational readership.</p>

    <p>The paper's signal collection is its photograph archives, which contain
nearly 100,000 items. A limited number of vintage images dates back as early as
the 1930-40s, but the strength of the collection lies in photographs from the
1960s-1990s.</p>

    <p>Topically, the archives are particularly strong in the fields of Black
business, politics (local, state, national, and international), the Civil
Rights Movement, entertainment, celebrities, leisure culture, sports, community
organizations, and community activism.</p>

    <p>For information about the Chicago Defender, visit <a
href="http://www.chicagodefender.com/">chicagodefender.com</a> or email <a
href="mailto:copyright@chicagodefender.com">copyright@chicagodefender.com</a>.</p>
  </institution>
  <institution>
    <h3 id="dusable">About the DuSable Museum of African American History</h3>

    <p><span class="snippet">Founded in 1961 and the oldest institution of its
kind in the U.S., the DuSable Museum of African American History mounts
exhibits that interpret African American and African history for the general
public.</span></p>

    <p>The exhibition holdings range from paintings by master African American
artists, a collection of over 2,000 African artifacts and a range of objects
from the early 1800's to the present. There is an extensive photographic
collection as well as costumes, works on paper, and sculpture.</p>

    <p>The Archives/Research Collection contains the personal papers of notable
African Americans, rare books, periodicals, manuscripts, political ephemera,
oral histories, film, video and communications equipment documenting African
and African American leadership, businesses, organizations and institutions.
The scope of the collections ranges from the southside of Chicago to national
and international history, art and culture.</p>

    <p>For information about the DuSable Museum of African American History, visit <a href="http://www.dusablemuseum.org/">dusablemuseum.org</a> or email <a href="mailto:mts@dusablemuseum.org">mts@dusablemuseum.org</a>.</p>
  </institution>
  <institution>
    <h3 id="chicagopubliclibrary">About the Chicago Public Library, Carter G.
Woodson Regional Library, Vivian G. Harsh Research Collection of Afro-American
History and Literature</h3>

    <p><span class="snippet">The Harsh Collection is the oldest and largest
African American Studies repository in the Midwest.</span> The collection was
founded in 1932 by Vivian G.  Harsh, the first black librarian to head a branch
of the Chicago Public Library. Harsh was an activist in Carter G. Woodson's
Association for the Study of Negro Life and History, she actively sought
donations for the collection from scholars, writers, and community activists.
Originally housed at the Hall Branch of the Chicago Public Library, located in
the heart of the Bronzeville community, the Harsh Collection began life as the
"Special Negro Collection". In the 1930s and 1940s the collection became a
central meeting place and resource during the Chicago Renaissance. By 1975 the
collection was moved to the new Carter G. Woodson Regional Library, where it
was renamed in honor of Vivian G. Harsh.</p>

    <p>Today the Harsh Collection holds more than 75,000 books, many of them
rare, over 500 periodical titles, some 15,000 reels of microfilm, nearly 5,000
clipping files, and some 175 manuscript and archival collections.  Although the
holdings include materials on peoples of African descent across the United
States and throughout the Diaspora, the collection's primary focus is on
documenting all aspects of African American history and culture in Chicago and
the state of Illinois. The scope of the manuscript and archival holdings is
especially diverse; these holdings include significant resources in literature,
art, music, journalism, social science, civil rights activism, religion, law,
business, labor, the medical professions, and social clubs.  Chronologically,
the strength of the collection lies primarily in the period 1930 to 2000.</p>

    <p>For information about the Harsh Collection, you may <a
href="http://www.chipublib.org/aboutcpl/ask_a_librarian.php">ask a
librarian</a> on the <a href="http://www.chipublib.org/">Chicago Public Library
website</a>.</p>
  </institution>
  <institution>
    <h3 id="northwesternuniversitylibrary">About the Northwestern University Library</h3>

    <p><span class="snippet">As one of the leading private research libraries
in the United States, Northwestern University Library serves the educational
and information needs of its students and faculty as well as scholars around
the world.</span>  Its collection of more than 4.6 million volumes is contained
in several sites located on Northwestern's Evanston and Chicago campuses.  The
Library includes a portfolio of distinguished special collections with
manuscript and archive collections relevant to UNCAP, notably:</p>

    <p><a
href="http://www.library.northwestern.edu/libraries-collections/evanston-campus/africana-collection">The
Melville J. Herskovits Library of African Studies</a> is the largest separate
Africana collection in the world. Its subject matter ranges from art, history,
literature, music, and religion to communications, management, and cooking.</p>

    <p><a
href="http://www.library.northwestern.edu/libraries-collections/evanston-campus/music-library">
The Music Library</a> is among the largest music collections in the U.S. It has
an unmatched strength in 20th century and contemporary classical music. The
Music Library's more than 300,000 volumes of books, scores, sound recordings,
and journals also include collections of original manuscripts and
correspondence.</p>

    <p>More than 225,000 rare books, periodicals, posters, manuscripts,
photographs, and other materials are found in the <a
href="http://www.library.northwestern.edu/libraries-collections/evanston-campus/special-collections">
Charles Deering McCormick Library of Special Collections</a>.  Holdings span
writing's entire history, from a cache of 5,000-year-old cuneiform Mesopotamian
tablets to an enormous trove of publications and ephemera documenting the
Women's Movement of the 1960s and 70s. Among the collection's many other
treasures are an extensive collection of materials on 20th century Dada,
Surrealist, Expressionist, and Futurist artists; two folios of Shakespeare's
plays; and original publications by W.B. Yeats and William S. Burroughs.</p>

    <p><a
href="http://www.library.northwestern.edu/libraries-collections/evanston-campus/university-archives">University
Archives</a> houses official Northwestern records of historical significance,
Northwestern-related serial publications and monographs, extensive audiovisual
materials, and hundreds of manuscript collections relating to University
faculty, students, alumni, and associates.</p>

    <p><a
href="http://www.library.northwestern.edu/about/library-administration/departments-offices/digital-collections">
Digital Library Collections</a>. Digital Collections Department advances the
University's teaching and research mission by providing digitization services
and support to Northwestern faculty and graduate students. The department
partners with other Library and University departments to provide these
services and to undertake special digitization projects that bring
Northwestern's unique and rare collections to researchers around the world.</p>
  </institution>
  <institution>
    <h3 id="sscac">About the South Side Community Art Center</h3>

    <p><span class="snippet">The South Side Community Art Center is the oldest
African American Art Center in existence. It has held classes in drawing,
painting, sculpture, printmaking, photography and crafts, even going beyond the
visual arts and offered literary and performing arts programs as well.</span>
The Center has an impressive collection of works by African-American artists
like Charles White, Henry Avery, Archibald Motley, Jr. and Marian Perkins.</p>

    <p>Although during the 1930's the WPA provided funds to hire staff and
faculty and to remodel the South Side Community Art Center's building, the
community had to pay for the lease and purchase of the building, for utilities,
and for art supplies. At the time of Depression this was especially difficult
for poor communities.</p>

    <p>The original fundraising efforts involved three years of activity,
including theater performances, card parties, a 'Mile of Dimes' street-corner
campaign, lectures and exhibitions held in churches, community centers, schools
and clubhouses. The most successful event was the Artists' and Models' Ball
held on October 23, 1939 at the Savoy Ballroom. This single event raised the
funds to acquire the building for the future Center.</p>

    <p>The South Side Community Art Center continues to act as a resource for
the arts community locally and abroad. It takes pride in its past and present
contributions to the development and showcasing of emerging and established
artists.</p>

    <p>For information about the South Side Community Art Center, <a
href="http://www.southsidecommunityartcenter.com/">visit their website</a>.</p>
  </institution>
  <institution>
    <h3 id="universityofchicago">About the University of Chicago Library</h3>

    <p><span class="snippet">Welcome to the University of Chicago Library, home
of one of the largest and richest research collections in the world.</span> Our
resources are housed in six library sites, all of which are located on the main
campus.  The Library supports study and teaching at the University by building
and creating information resources and providing services that enhance their
usefulness, accessibility, and availability over time. Central to our mission
is the excellence in collections we develop, the excellence in information we
provide, the excellence in services we offer, and the excellence in
environments we create. Our print resources total more than seven million
printed works, increasing at the rate of 150,000 volumes per year. Over thirty
million manuscripts and archival pieces, 420,000 maps and aerial photographs,
and large sets of microform materials complement the printed collections. The
distinctive rare book, manuscript and archival holdings of the Special
Collections Research Center are available for your study.</p>

    <p>For information about collections at the University of Chicago Library,
you may <a href="http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/ask/SCRC.html">contact the
Special Collections Research Center</a>.</p>
  </institution>
</institutions>
